<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8" standalone="yes"?>
<rss version="2.0" xmlns:atom="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">
  <channel>
    <title>silasprincipe on resources</title>
    <link>http://www.example.com/authors/silasprincipe/</link>
    <description>Recent content in silasprincipe on resources</description>
    <generator>Hugo -- gohugo.io</generator>
    <lastBuildDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</lastBuildDate><atom:link href="http://www.example.com/authors/silasprincipe/index.xml" rel="self" type="application/rss+xml" />
    <item>
      <title>Using DuckDB to query the OBIS full export - Part 1</title>
      <link>http://www.example.com/tutorials/duckdb-part1/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.example.com/tutorials/duckdb-part1/</guid>
      <description>The OBIS full export OBIS has more than 160 million occurrence records available (and growing!). Previously you could download the full export as a single Parquet file and do a range of analysis with it, but since recently the full export became available in AWS through the Open Data Program. This came with a total update of the way the data is offered. Now the full export is offered as a dataset of GeoParquet files, what opens up a world of possibilities in doing spatial analysis with the data, and also make analysis much more efficient and cloud performant.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using DuckDB to query the OBIS full export - Part 2 (spatial extension)</title>
      <link>http://www.example.com/tutorials/duckdb-part2/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.example.com/tutorials/duckdb-part2/</guid>
      <description>Spatial extension of DuckDB In a previous tutorial we learned about DuckDB and how it can be used to query Parquet datasets from OBIS. As we shared, the new full export is a GeoParquet dataset, meaning that it add spatial functionalities to the standard Parquet format. DuckDB has a powerful spatial extension, which we will present in this tutorial. Of course, we will just give you a glimpse of what you can do with this extension, and you should invest a few minutes to explore the full documentation.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using DuckDB to query the OBIS full export - Part 3 (`duckplyr` package)</title>
      <link>http://www.example.com/tutorials/duckdb-part3/</link>
      <pubDate>Fri, 26 Sep 2025 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.example.com/tutorials/duckdb-part3/</guid>
      <description>duckplyr In the two previous tutorials we learned about how to use DuckDB for querying the Parquet exports and about the DuckDB spatial extension. Here we will explore the R package duckplyr, a drop-in replacement for DuckDB on R which uses the tidyverse grammar.
Again, we will work with a local copy of the full export, which you can download from here: https://obis.org/data/access/. You can also explore together through the Jupyter Notebook (download it locally or open it through Google Colab by clicking here).</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Matching environmental information with OBIS occurrences</title>
      <link>http://www.example.com/tutorials/env-data/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.example.com/tutorials/env-data/</guid>
      <description>Obtaining environmental information for species occurrences For many research questions, we are interested in the environmental conditions where a certain species, population, or community lives. OBIS already provides some environmental data along with the records. For example, if you download records for the species Actinia equina, you can obtain values for sea surface temperature (SST), salinity (SSS), and bathymetry:
library(robis) occ &amp;lt;- occurrence(&amp;quot;Actinia equina&amp;quot;) ## Retrieved 5000 records of approximately 9583 (52%)Retrieved 9583 records of ## approximately 9583 (100%) head(occ[,c(&amp;quot;sst&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;sss&amp;quot;, &amp;quot;bathymetry&amp;quot;)], 4) ## # A tibble: 4 × 3 ## sst sss bathymetry ## &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; &amp;lt;dbl&amp;gt; ## 1 10.</description>
    </item>
    
    <item>
      <title>Using the Parquet format with OBIS data</title>
      <link>http://www.example.com/tutorials/arrow-obis/</link>
      <pubDate>Tue, 01 Aug 2023 00:00:00 +0000</pubDate>
      
      <guid>http://www.example.com/tutorials/arrow-obis/</guid>
      <description>What is Parquet? Parquet is a lightweight format designed for columnar storage. Its main difference when compared to other formats like csv is that Parquet is column-oriented (while csv is row-oriented). This means that Parquet is much more efficient for data accessing.To illustrate, consider the scenario of extracting data from a specific column in a CSV file. This operation entails reading through all rows across all columns. In contrast, Parquet enables selective access solely to the required column, minimizing unnecessary data retrieval.</description>
    </item>
    
  </channel>
</rss>
